Being Different is Normal
It's a pleasure to meet you.
I've wanted to ask a question
since I heard your Dharma talk on April 7
but I didn't have the courage
to ask before.
I learned about Buddhism by hanging
a lantern with my acquaintance.
After I hung the lantern,
I didn't go to the temple often.
To motivate myself a bit more,
I've registered a beginner's Dharma class.
It's been a month since I started the class
Maybe this is due to my lack of faith
but I feel uneasy when I hear
the repeated request from the teacher
regarding the lantern donation
at the end of each class.
I did the lantern donation for my family
voluntarily for the first time.
With the repeated requests,
I feel obligated to do it.
And this makes me uneasy,
questioning my lack of faith.
Then I heard that the abbot will be
having a book launch at a hotel.
I think it is inappropriate to have
a book launch in a hotel by an abbot.
I know Christianity gets blamed
from the public because it's too worldly.
And these days I start to wonder
if Buddhism is following the same path,
I'd like to ask if my lack of faith is
causing this critical thought.
Nobody is the same in this world, right?
Are politicians all the same or not?
Not all pastors are bad, right?
And not all of them are good either.
It's the same with monks.
Monks are all different
And temples are all different.
So then what's normal?
All to be the same, or to be different?
It's normal to be different.
Right. So every happening in this world is
just one of happenings
that are possible in this world.
There are monks who lead pure life
with belief in non-possession.
Then there are monks
who are greedier than ordinary people
and relish in worldly pleasures.
Among monks,
there are all sorts of different types.
Among ordinary group of people,
some of them are humble and kind, right?
There are bright smart students and then
there are those who dozes off in a school class.
Among teachers who complain
about these students,
some of them fall asleep during my lecture.
Among principals who complain
about these teachers,
some fall asleep during my lecture.
The same goes with school administrators.
There are some who fall asleep as well.
This is just how the world is.
There are all kinds of different people
in this world.
But you insist your own way
about monks, temples, and whatever.
Wouldn't it be nice
if that were the case?
But the real world is not so.
It's very diverse.
So, see the world like this.
This temple asks for lantern donations,
and that temple doesn't mention it.
Instead of judging them good or bad,
just acknowledge that this temple is
trying to get lots of lantern donations,
and that temple doesn't know how to
get donations in this day and age
Just accept like that.
There's someone who publishes tens of
books who never holds a book launch event
Then theres someone who organizes
a big launch with their first book.
Some do elaborate way,
others do simple way,
there are these differences.
So instead of judging
what is right or wrong,
just observe it as a phenomenon.
There are flowers large or small in size,
yellow or red in color,
having this or that shape.
Just see all these diversities.
With your obsession about monks
and others to be certain way,
you judge them constantly.
This would make you exhausted.
You criticize a monk visiting the temple.
You criticize Buddhism
while studying Buddhism.
You criticize Korea while living here.
This would diminish your pride.
This isn't due to lack of faith.
It has nothing to do with faith.
This could be
from the misunderstanding of Dharma.
So, are all things the same? No.
So then how should I live in this reality?
If you believe a monk should be frugal,
then go to a temple that has
a frugal monk. Understand?
If you believe that lantern donations
should be voluntary,
and not be pressured by others, then
do not judge the temple is bad
when it asks donations.
Just go to another temple that doesn't ask
(Questioner) Yes. I understand.